<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<chapter>
  <?dbhtml filename="reference.html"?>
  <title>API Reference</title>

  <section>
  <?dbhtml filename="credentials.html"?>
  <title>Credential Management</title>

  <para>
  Most Active Directory operations require authentication. The default
  authentication mechanism in AD is Kerberos. Unfortunately, it has always
  been difficult to use Kerberos authentication with AD. It required for
  example to have a properly configured <filename>/etc/krb5.conf</filename>
  listing the realms you want to use and the Kerbers servers for those realms.
  </para>

  <para>
  Fortunately Python-AD simplifies AD credential management significantly. It
  does not require any system configuration and all functionality is embedded
  in a single class named <classname>Creds</classname>. This class is
  available from the Python package <package>ad</package>
  </para>

  <programlisting>
  from ad import Creds
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  The constructor for the <classname>Creds</classname> class takes one
  argument: <parameter>domain</parameter>. This parameter specifies the
  default AD domain for credential management.
  </para>

  <programlisting>
  class Creds(object):
      """Credential management."""

      def __init__(self, domain):
          """Constructor."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  The <parameter>domain</parameter> parameter is used as a default when
  principals are used without domain name. Credentials in any other domains
  can be acquired as long as the domain is part of the same AD forest.
  </para>

  <para>
  The <classname>Creds</classname> class has the following methods:
  </para>

  <programlisting>

      def acquire(self, principal, password=None, keytab=None, server=None):
          """Acquire credentials."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  The <function>acquire()</function> function acquires credentials for
  principal <parameter>principal</parameter>. The principal can either a
  unqualified principal, in which case the default domain is assumed, or a
  principal in the form of <varname>user@domain</varname> in which case
  <varname>domain</varname> must be a domain in the same AD forest as the
  default domain. The <parameter>password</parameter> contains the password to
  the principal. If no password is given, a keytab will be used. This keytab
  is can be specified by the <parameter>keytab</parameter> parameter. If this
  parameter is not present either, the default system keytab is used.  The
  <parameter>server</parameter> argument overrides the default Kerberos server
  to acquire credentials from. If this argument is not given, a suitable
  Kerberos server is autodetected.
  </para>

  <programlisting>

      def load(self):
          """Load credentials from the OS."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  The function <function>load()</function> loads credentials from the default
  operating system credentials store. It raises an exception in case no
  credentials are available.
  </para>

  <programlisting>

      def principal(self):
          """Return the current principal."""
  </programlisting>
  
  <para>
  The <function>principal()</function> method returns the current principal,
  i.e. the principal that was last succesfully used in a call to
  <function>acquire()</function>.
  </para>

  <programlisting>

      def release(self):
          """Release all credentials."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  The <function>release()</function> method releases the currently held
  credentials.  It is called automatically from the
  <classname>Creds</classname> destructor.
  </para>

  <para>
  Once credentials are acquired with <function>acquire()</function>, they need
  to be activated before they can be used. This is required because
  credentials are a process-global resource and they need to be installed in a
  place where other classes in Python-AD will be able to find them. Credential
  activation is done by calling a function called
  <function>activate()</function> as follows:
  </para>

  <programlisting>
  from ad import activate
  activate(creds)
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  The code fragment above will make the <varname>creds</varname> object the
  globally active credentials. The <function>activate()</function> can be
  called multiple times on different objects. The semantics are that the
  object on which <function>activate()</function> was called last will be the
  active credentials. If active credentials are released by calling the
  <function>release()</function> method of a <classname>Creds</classname>
  instance, then the credentials that were previously active are activated. If
  no previously activated credentials exist, there will be no credentials
  available after this call.
  </para>

  </section>

  <section>
  <?dbhtml filename="client.html"?>
  <title>AD Client Interface</title>

  <para>
  The actual operations on Active Directory are grouped in a single class
  called <classname>Client</classname>. This class is available from the
  <package>ad</package> package.
  </para>

  <programlisting>
  from ad import Client
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  The constructor to the <classname>Client</classname> class takes one
  argument: the domain.
  </para>

  <programlisting>
  class Client(object):
      """AD client interface."""

      def __init__(self, domain):
        """Constructor."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  The <parameter>domain</parameter> parameter sets the default domain for the
  <classname>Client</classname> class. As with the
  <classname>Creds</classname> class, the requirement to specify the domain
  does not mean that operations through the client are limited to the
  specified domain: all operations are available to any domain that is part of
  the same forest.
  </para>

  <para>
  Instances of the <classname>Client</classname> class will try to access the
  globally installed <classname>Creds</classname> instance. Therefore you must
  ensure that credentials are available before you use any functionality in
  this class.
  </para>

  <para>
  The following methods are provided by the <classname>Client</classname>
  class:
  </para>

  <programlisting>

      def domain_name_from_dn(self, dn):
          """Given a DN, return a domain."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  The function <function>domain_name_from_dn()</function> is a utility
  function that, given an LDAP distinguished name, will return the Active
  Directory domain name. For example, if the <parameter>dn</parameter>
  parameter is set to <literal>cn=users,dc=freeadi,dc=org</literal>, the
  return value of this method will be <literal>FREEADI.ORG</literal>.
  </para>

  <programlisting>

      def dn_from_domain_name(self, name):
          """Given a domain name, return a DN."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  The function <function>dn_from_domain_name()</function> is the inverse of
  <function>domain_name_from_dn()</function>. For example, if
  <parameter>name</parameter> is set to <literal>LINUX.FREEADI.ORG</literal>,
  the return value of this method will be
  <literal>dc=linux,dc=freeadi,dc=org</literal>.
  </para>

  <programlisting>

      def domain(self):
          """Return the domain name of the current domain."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  This method returns the current default domain.
  </para>

  <programlisting>

      def domain_base(self):
          """Return the base DN of the domain."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  The method <function>domain_base()</function> returns the LDAP base DN for
  the curent domain. If <literal>client</literal> is an instance of
  <classname>Client</classname>, then this is equivalent to
  <literal>client.dn_from_domain_name(client.domain())</literal>.
  </para>

  <programlisting>
      def forest(self):
          """Return the domain name of the forest root."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  This method returns the root of the forest for the current domain. In case
  the current domain is a child domain, this will return something different
  than the <function>domain()</function> method.
  </para>

  <programlisting>
      def forest_base(self):
          """Return the base DN of the forest root."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  The <function>forest_base()</function> method returns the LDAP base DN for
  the forest. This function is equivalent to
  <literal>client.dn_from_domain_name(client.forest())</literal>.
  </para>

  <programlisting>
      def schema_base(self):
          """Return the base DN of the schema naming_context."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  This method returns the LDAP base DN for the schema naming context for the
  Active Directory forest.
  </para>

  <programlisting>
      def configuration_base(self):
          """Return the base DN of the configuration naming_context."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  This method returns the LDAP base DN for the configuration namign context
  for the Active Directory forest.
  </para>

  <programlisting>
      def naming_contexts(self):
          """Return a list of all naming_contexts."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  The <function>naming_contexts()</function> returns a list of all naming
  contexts in the forest. The term naming context is the Microsoft name for a
  directory partition. Each naming context is present on one or multiple
  domain controllers, and each domain controller normally has multiple naming
  contexts.
  </para>

  <programlisting>
      def domains(self):
          """Return a list of all domains in the forest."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  This function returns a list of all domains that are present in the forest.
  </para>

  <programlisting>
      def close(self):
          """Close any active LDAP connection."""
  </programlisting>
  
  <para>
  The <function>close()</function> closes all currently open connections to
  the Active Directory.
  </para>

  <programlisting>
      def search(self, filter=None, base=None, scope=None, attrs=None,
                 server=None, scheme=None):
          """Search the Active Directory."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  The <function>search()</function> method is probably the most important
  function in Python-AD. It searches the Active Directory and returns a list
  of objects that match the query. The <parameter>filter</parameter> argument
  specifies the LDAP search filter. If it is absent, the default filter is
  <literal>(objectClass=*)</literal>. The <parameter>base</parameter>
  arguments gives the LDAP search base. This search base must either be blank
  (<literal>''</literal>) in which case the rootDSE is searched, or it must be
  within one of the naming contexts of the forest. The
  <parameter>scope</parameter> parameter must be a string of the value
  <literal>'base'</literal>, <literal>'onelevel'</literal> or
  <literal>'subtree'</literal>. For compatibility reasons, the
  <literal>SCOPE_*</literal> constants as defined by  Python-LDAP are accepted
  as well.  The <parameter>attrs</parameter> parameter specifies the attributes
  to request. If it is given, it must be a list of strings. If it is not
  specified, then the default is to request all attributes. The
  <parameter>server</parameter> parameter is another optional parameter that
  specifies the server to bind to. Normally, Python-AD operates in
  <emphasis>serverless binding</emphasis> mode. In this mode, a suitable
  domain controller is selected automatically. In some situation this may not
  be desidered however and for these situations the
  <parameter>server</parameter> can be used. Finally the
  <parameter>scheme</parameter> parameter specifies the search scheme. It must
  be one of <literal>'ldap'</literal> (the default) or <literal>'gc'</literal>
  to search the global catalog.
  </para>

  <para>
  The return value of <function>search()</function> is a list of 2-tuples.
  Each tuple consists of a distinguished name and a dictionary of attributes.
  The dictionary has string keys (the attribute names) and a list of strings
  as it values (the attribute values).
  </para>

  <programlisting>
      def add(self, dn, attrs, server=None):
          """Add a new object to Active Directory."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  The <function>add()</function> function adds an object to the directory. The
  parameter <parameter>dn</parameter> specifies the distinguished name of the
  attribute to be added. The parameter <parameter>attrs</parameter> specifies
  the attributes of the object. It must be a list of 2-tuples, with the first
  tuple entry the attribute name, and the second tuple entry a list of strings
  containing the attribute values. The <parameter>server</parameter> parameter
  can be used to override the default binding behaviour and has the same
  meaning as for <function>search()</function>.
  </para>

  <programlisting>
      def modify(self, dn, mods, server=None):
          """Modify an LDAP object."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  The <function>modify()</function> method modifies an existing object in the
  directory. The <parameter>dn</parameter> parameter specifies the
  distinguished name of the object modify, while <parameter>mods</parameter>
  specifies the modifications. The latter must be a list of 3-tuples. Each
  tuple consists of the modify operation (one of <literal>'add'</literal>,
  <literal>'replace'</literal> or <literal>'delete'</literal> to add, replace
  or delete an attribute value respectively -- the Python-LDAP
  <literal>MOD_*</literal> constants are supported for compatibility), the
  attribute name, and the attribute value. The latter must be a list of
  strings. The <parameter>server</parameter> parameter can be used to override
  the default binding behaviour and has the same meaning as for
  <function>search()</function>.
  </para>

  <programlisting>
      def delete(self, dn, server=None):
          """Delete the LDAP object referenced by `dn'."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  The <function>delete()</function> method removes an object from the
  directory. The <parameter>dn</parameter> parameter specifies the
  distinguished name of the object to remove. The <parameter>server</parameter>
  parameter can be used to override the default binding behaviour and has the
  same meaning as for <function>search()</function>.
  </para>

  <programlisting>
      def modrdn(self, dn, newrdn, delold=True, server=None):
          """Change the RDN of an object in Active Direcotry."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  The <function>modrdn()</function> method modifies the relative distinuished
  name of the LDAP object with distinguished name <parameter>dn</parameter> to
  the value specified by the <parameter>newrdn</parameter>, which must be in
  the form of <literal>"attr=value"</literal>. The
  <parameter>delold</parameter> specifies whether the old RDN value is
  retained or not. The <parameter>server</parameter> parameter has the same
  meaning as for <function>search()</function>.
  </para>

  <programlisting>
      def rename(self, dn, newrdn, newsuperior=None, delold=True, server=None):
          """Change the RDN of an object in Active Directory, and optionally
          move it to a new part of the tree."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  The <function>rename()</function> method is like
  <function>modrdn()</function> but is also allows the object to be moved to a
  new place in the directory by means of the
  <parameter>newsuperior</parameter> parameter.
  </para>

  <programlisting>
      def set_password(self, principal, password, server=None):
          """Set the password of `principal' to `password'."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  This function sets the password for <parameter>principal</parameter> to
  <parameter>password</parameter>. The <parameter>server</parameter> parameter
  can again be used to override the default server binding as for the
  <function>search()</function> method.
  </para>

  <programlisting>
      def change_password(self, principal, oldpass, newpass, server=None):
          """Change the password of `principal' to `password'."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  This function changes the password for principal
  <parameter>principal</parameter>. The old password must be given in
  <parameter>oldpass</parameter> and the new password in
  <parameter>newpass</parameter>.
  </para>

  </section>

  <section>
  <?dbhtml filename="locator.html"?>
  <title>Resource Location</title>

  <para>
  Resource location is an problem that is normally handled transparently by
  Python-AD. In the default situation, domain controllers are looked up
  automatically by a global instance of the <classname>Locator</classname>
  class. It is possible however to use this class directly. This is most
  useful when targetting a specific domain controller with the
  <parameter>server</parameter> argument that many methods of the
  <classname>Client</classname> class accept.
  </para>


  The <classname>Locator</classname> class is available from the
  <package>ad</package> package:

  <programlisting>
  from ad import Locator
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  The constructor takes one optional parameter: the site.
  </para>

  <programlisting>
    class Locator(object):
        """Locate domain controllers.

        def __init__(self, site=None):
            """Constructor."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  The <parameter>site</parameter> specifies the AD site the current system is
  in. Normally this value is autodetected, but in some situations you may want
  to override this.
  </para>

  <para>
  The <classname>Locator</classname> class defines the following methods:
  </para>

  <programlisting>
      def locate(self, domain, role=None):
          """Locate one domain controller."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  The <function>locate()</function> method locates one domain controller for
  the domain <parameter>domain</parameter>. The optional parameter
  <parameter>role</parameter>, if given, specifies the desired role of the
  domain controller. This can be one of <literal>'dc'</literal>,
  <literal>'gc'</literal> or <literal>'pdc'</literal> for a normal domain
  controller, a global catalog, or the domain controller with the primary
  domain controller emulator role respectively. The default is to locate an
  ordinary domain controller. The return value of this method is a string
  containing the host name of the domain controller. If no domain controller
  is found, an exception is raised.
  </para>

  <programlisting>
      def locate_many(self, domain, role=None, maxservers=None):
          """Locate a list of up to `maxservers' of domain controllers."""
  </programlisting>

  <para>
  This method locates up to <parameter>maxservers</parameter> domain
  controllers. The <parameter>domain</parameter> and
  <parameter>role</parameter> parameters are as for
  <function>locate()</function>. The return value is a list of strings
  containing the host names of the selected domain controllers. If no domain
  controllers are found, an empty list is returned.
  </para>

  </section>

  <section>
  <?dbhtml filename="error.html"?>
  <title>Error Handling</title>

  Two exceptions are defined for error handling. It is recommended to import
  the exception as per the code fragment below:

  <programlisting>
  from ad import Error as ADError
  from ad import LDAPError
  </programlisting>

  The <classname>ADError</classname> exception is raised for all errors that
  are encountered by Python-AD. The <classname>LDAPError</classname> exception
  is imported from Python-LDAP and is raised when an exception is raised by
  that module. Therefore, to ensure that all exceptions are caught, you always
  need to capture both exceptions, as illustrated by the example below:

  <programlisting>
  client = Client(domain)
  try:
      client.add(dn, attrs)
  except (ADError, LDAPError):
      pass
  </programlisting>

  </section>

</chapter>
